Guide to the Congregation Beth Israel collection, 1854-2012 MS 711
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Congregation Beth Israel collection
1854-2012
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Eskowitz, Sheryl
MS 711
4.25 Linear Feet 8 boxes
The Congregation Beth Israel Collection offers a glimpse into the day-to-day goings-on of Congregation Beth Israel, with documents spanning a century of the Jewish temple's existence. Books, memorabilia, directories, programs, sermons, and church bulletins from different decades show the similarities and changes at Beth Israel as it continues to grow with the rest of Houston's Jewish Community.
Biographical / Historical
Established in 1854, Congregation Beth Israel is one of the oldest Jewish congregations in Texas, and boasts a long and fascinating history. A center of the national Reform Jewish movement, the congregation serves more than 1,600 households throughout the greater Houston area. The campus can be found in Southwest Houston and offers weekly Shabbat Services, Torah study, and a number of educational, cultural, and social programs. Congregation Beth Israel also supports a religious school in the Miriam Browning Jewish Learning Center, and the Shlenker school, providing over 800 students with quality education, grounded in Jewish values. The clergy team is currently (2019) led by Senior Rabbi David Lyon.
A famous figure on the Houston Jewish scene, Rabbi Hyman Judah Schachtel served as the Senior Rabbi at Congregation Beth Israel from 1943 to 1975, and as Rabbi Emeritus from 1975 to 1990. Hugely influential, Schachtel wrote a number of books including "The Real Enjoyment of Living" and "The Life You Want to Live," hosted his own radio show on KODA-FM, and delivered the inaugural prayer for President Lyndon B. Johnson in Washington D.C. in 1965.
Content Description
The Congregation Beth Israel Collection is made up of programs and catalogues, directories, historical documents, memorabilia, books, sermons, and temple bulletins depicting the day-to-day running of one of Houston's largest congregations. The materials are in good condition and range in date from 1854 to 2012. Researchers interested in the Houston Jewish community, particularly the events and goings-on associated with Congregation Beth Israel would find this collection insightful.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
A portion of the materials were donated by Judy Weidman, of Congregation Beth-Israel, Houston, Texas, via Dr. Josh Furman, Rice University in November of 2017. The remainder of the materials were donated by Ann Schactel, via Dr. Josh Furman during February of 2018.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged in six series, as follows:
Series I: Programs and Catalogues
Series II: Directories
Series III: History and Memorabilia
Series IV: Books
Series V: Temple Bulletins Series VI: Oversize
Related Materials
Drawn from one of the same donations, more materials regarding Rabbi Schachtel can be found in the Rabbi Hyman Judah Schachtel papers, MS 730.
Index Terms
Subjects
Jews and Jewish life; Judaism -- Customs and practices; Church bulletins; Religion
Document Types
Correspondence; Programs (Publications); photographs; Programs (Publications); exhibition catalogs; directories; Collectibles; books; sermons
Subjects (Persons)
Weidman, Judy
Subjects (Corporations)
Congregation Beth Israel (Houston, Tex.)
- Series I: Programs and Catalogues
  - "Hallelujah Houston" Program (2), 1854-1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Program Honoring Rabbi's Barnston & Schactel, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Service Programs, 1961-2017 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - T.O.F.T.Y. Yearbook, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Hello Follies" program, 1974-11-02-1974-11-03 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Center Ring" Program, 1977-11-12-1977-11-13 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Contemporary Lights, A Celebration of Chanukah" Catalogue, 1996-11-07-1996-12-31 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Shabbat Service program honoring Rabbi Karff, 1999-05-14 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "L'Dor V'Dor" 150th Anniversary musical salute program (2), 2004-05-22 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Unleashed" - Margolis Gallery Exhibition Program, 2005-12-10 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Book of Remembrance: Yom Kippur Memorial Service, 2012-09-26 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series II: Directories
  - The Sisterhood Directories (3), 1964-1965, 1977-1978, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Membership Directory, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Congregation Beth Israel Directory, 1998 (2), 2000, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Series III: History and Memorabilia
  - "Basic Principles" of Congregation Beth Israel, ca. 1943 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Confirmation Class Photos, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1935, 1997, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "Storm Over Zion," Time Article, January, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Schactel's Inaugural Prayer for LBJ, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Congregation Beth Israel Dedication Plate, 1967-12-01 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Congregation By-laws, January 1971 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Religious Reflections, 1971, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - History of the Jewish Literary Society (photocopy), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Ritual & Music Committee Chairman's Files, 1980-1984 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Congregation Roster, 1981-06-01 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - By-Laws (Amended 1989) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Head of School Report, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - "100 Years of Congregation Beth Yeshurun", 2003 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Concept Art & Descriptions of Beth Israel Building, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Postcards depicting Beth Israel Building, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Beth Israel Stationary, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Book of Honors: In tribute to Women of Reform Judaism, 1999-2000 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Congregation Survey Results, n.d. (2) (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
- Series IV: Books
  - Union Haggadah Revised (2), 1923 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - The Holy Scriptures, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Union Prayer Book [Andy Schactel], 1953 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Heavenly Cooking from Space City U.S.A., 1953 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Series V: Temple Bulletins
  - Volume 102 (16), 1956-1957 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Volume 103 (21), 1957-1962 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Volume 104 (22), 1958-1959 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Volume 105 (20), 1959-1960 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Volume 106 (15), 1960-1961 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Volume 108 (38), 1961-1962 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Volumes 109 (1), 116 (1), 122 (2), 124 (1), 126 (2), 130 (2), 131 (2), 134 (1) and 136 (1), 1962-1990 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Volume 138 (16), 1991-1992 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Volume 139 (16), 1992-1993 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Volume 143 (5), 1996-1997 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Volume 144 (21), 1997-1998 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Volumes 145 (8) & 146 (2), 1998-2000 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Volume 167 No.1, 2020-08 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Series VI: Oversize
  - Concept Art Book for the new Temple Beth Israel, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Series VII: Addenda
  - Booklets of Rabbi Samuel Karff's sermons, 1976-1992 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Booklets of Rabbi Samuel Karff's sermons, 1993-1995 (Box 8, Folder 2)